Ashish Bansal

Machine Learning/AI Data Scientist

10 years of experience out of which 4+ years of research and development experience in ML/DL. Blogger, you-tuber Tech enthusiastic consistently endeavour to learn new technologies, business domains and latest industry trends for achieving company goals.

🔀 ashishb21@gmail.com

Bathinda (Punjab)

in linkedin.com/in/ashishbansal1

medium.com/@ashishb21

07838040773

techplanetai.com, www.youtube.com/c/TechplanetAI/

github.com/ashishb21

WORK EXPERIENCE

Sr Software Engineer Lexis Nexis Pvt Ltd

07/2021 - Present

Gurugram,India

Achievements/Tasks

- Working on Metadata extraction project for pdf documents of legal case documents using NLP and pdfminer.
- Deploying API using FastAPI to cloud using CD/CI pipelines.
- Worked on Case identification legislation and AutoMarkup API which identifies legislation into legal documents using DL and text-based approach.
- Developed a single process to combine all the services to yield good result and better output.

Technical Analyst Coforge Pvt Ltd

10/2020 - 07/2021

Noida,India

Achievements/Tasks

- Working for NNIP Investment Fintech to provide an intelligent search for their SEC filings data using NLP and AWS Elastic Search Service.
- Processed 10-K and 10-Q filings in AWS Elastic Search for fast searching of data.
- Provided intelligent search API using Python FastAPI framework.
- Triggered Pipeline using AWS Lambda and AWS CloudFormation and Integrated the flow using Gitlab CD/CI.

Data Science Specialist Collaborative Intelligence Pvt Ltd

10/2019 - 06/2020

Guruaram.India

Achievements/Tasks

- Working on **Tyrambak** (Object detection and License Plate Detection) using ML and DL models of the moving vehicles and transmitting data on the entry and exit.
- Working on building end-to-end ML training and deployment on the dataset using YOLO.
- Preprocessing of video feed (5MP, 2MP) using Image Processing Techniques and OpenCV.

SKILLS



EDUCATION

MTech (AR VR) Executive

IIT Jodhour

08/2022 - Present

IOP CS231 Deep Learning

IIIT Delhi

01/2019 - 05/2019

IOP CS343/543 Machine Learning

IIIT Delhi

07/2018 - 12/2018

B.E (Information Technology) DYPIET Pune University

03/2005 - 06/2009

First class with distinction

CERTIFICATION & COURSES

TCS iON ProCert - Artificial Intelligence

Business Analytics and Text Mining Modeling using Python NPTFI

Python for Data Science

Machine Learning for Engineering and Science Applications NPTEL

WORK EXPERIENCE

Data Science Engineer/SDET LeadEseye Global Pvt Ltd

03/2017 - 08/2018

Noida, India

Achievements/Tasks

- Worked for Messaging V4 which is messaging system using to connect IOT with centralized server.
- Built a Machine Learning (Logistic Regression) model which predicts the crash according to the metrics recorded in IOT device.
- Apply machine learning algorithms, statistical data analysis, computational linguistics, and similar tools to find useful patterns in data collections.
- Build API/Web automation frameworks from scratch using Rest Assured, Protractor (e2e framework for angular/angular Js app) Postman, SoapUI.
- Travel onsite to UK office for KT and working with offshore team for product delivery and testing.

SDET Lead

Snapdeal

08/2013 - 03/2017

Gurugram, India

Achievements/Tasks

- Worked on various e-commerce products and portals (OLP, Delivery Boy App and Janus)
- Verifying change requests and defect, documenting, tracking and communicating test plans, test results and unresolved problems.
- Integration testing of various components. (Vulcan, Prtouch, Freecharge)
- Build API automation framework and automated business flows of app using Postman and integrated on Jenkins.
- Measured performance of API's using JMeter.

QA EngineerIbibo Web Pvt Ltd

04/2011 - 07/2013

Gurugram,India

Achievements/Tasks

- Worked as a security and performance test engineer in Ibibo products Goibibo Payu Tradus.
- Automated security testing of Ibibo applications using Acunetix web scanner and Armorize Codesecure.
- Manually Identified XSS, CSRF, SQL Injection.

CERTIFICATION & COURSES

Applied Machine Learning in Python

Getting Started with Tensorflow 2

The Joy of Computing using Python NPTEL

Introduction to Data Science in Python Coursera

CSM (Certified Scrum Master)

Scrum Alliance

Getting started with AWS Machine Learning Coursera

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Teaching Instructor

Truneek

Tasks/Achievements

 7 Day course online Python with Data Science (NumPy, Pandas, Matplotlib).

Teaching Instructor IBM

Tasks/Achievements

 Delivered 4-day online training with IBM on programming with Python, Datascience and OpenCV

PUBLICATIONS

Blog

Need for Feature Engineering in Machine Learning 28/04/2019

https://towardsdatascience.com/need-for-feature-engineering-in-machine-learning-897df2ed00e6

Blog

Image Enhancement Techniques using OpenCV and Python

26/05/2020

https://towardsdatascience.com/image-enhancement-techniques-using-opency-and-python-9191d5c30d45

Blog

All You Need to Know about Elastic Search Queries with AWS

26/09/2021

https://medium.com/@ashishb21/all-you-need-to-know-about-elastic-search-queries-with-aws-26ea626aec1e

Youtube

Python Fastapi project using SAM Serverless | AWS Deployment | Lambda with API Gateway Fast API | 03/06/2022

https://youtu.be/9ciujhGdAOs